בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף Daf is ל"ז, Lamed Zayin, 37,
and we pick up with some משנה Mishna on the bottom of
ל"ו עמוד ב', Lamed Vav Amud Bet, and we now move from
discussions of categorizing מצוות Mitzvot between men and women into categorizing מצוות
Mitzvot between those that apply everywhere and those that apply only in
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So again, it's clear that the theme here
of this פרק Perek is to sort of pull a lot of
things together and create categories, categorizing all the different things that can
be acquired and the ways in which they can be acquired,
and then sort of a categorizing here
of about מצוות Mitzvot and how they are sort of allocated and
who, which ones apply to men, women, in ישראל, Yisrael, out of
ישראל Yisrael and so on. It sort of reminds one of the
אין בין Ain Bein in מגילה Megilla where you wind up covering
like a wide scope of things.
And here, it's not exactly as much of a linguistic theme, there
might be a כל מצוות הבן על האב Kol Mitzvas Haben Al
Ha'av which does apply to parents, to fathers versus sons, to children
to their parents. So there's the כל Kol type of a word
going on here, but it seems also just more the general theme
of
categorizing broad scopes of things, of categorizing קניינים Kinyanim and categorizing מצוות.
Mitzvot. Anyway, with that in mind, we have this משנה Mishna here,
we pick up with this משנה Mishna on the bottom of ל"ו
עמוד ב'. Lamed Vav Amud Bet.
Extremely long first פרק, Perek, is it?
It is a very long first פרק, Perek, I think it's the
longest of the
פרקים Prakim in ש"ס. Shas. כל מצווה שהיא תלויה בארץ, Kol mitzva
she'hi teluya ba'aretz, any מצווה Mitzva that is dependent on the land,
אינה נוהגת אלא בארץ, Eina noheget ela ba'aretz, applies only in the
land of Israel, ושאינה תלויה בארץ, Veshe'eina teluya ba'aretz, and is not
dependent on the land, נוהגת בין בארץ ובין בחוץ לארץ, Noheget bein
ba'aretz uvein bechutz la'aretz, applies whether in the land of Israel or
outside of the land of
Israel, חוץ מן הערלה והכלאיים, Chutz min ha'orlah vehakilayim, with the exception
of ערלה Orlah and כלאיים. Kilayim. ערלה, Orlah, the first three years
something is planted; כלאיים, Kilayim, a mixture of a crossbreeding of seeds;
that that actually applies even in בחוץ לארץ, Bechutz la'aretz, outside of
the land, even though that has to do, that is related to
the earth. It's about things that grow on the earth, in the
earth. Nevertheless, by the way, within ערלה Orlah and כלאיים, Kilayim, there
is, according to a משנה, Mishna,
ערלה Orlah is הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha LeMoshe MiSinai and כלאיים Kilayim
is only דרבנן, Derabbanan, which is a little
ironic. Like if I had to guess which of those is more
weighty, I would have guessed or like more logical to apply in
חוץ לארץ, Chutz la'aretz, I would have picked כלאיים Kilayim because כלאיים
Kilayim is a sense of like the same way there's other forms
of כלאיים, Kilayim, crossbreeding animals and wool and linen and all those
other types of things. Okay, this is a כלאיים Kilayim that has
to do with seeds, but not necessarily having to do with the
land of Israel, even though it is a way in which you
crossbreed something in the land. Nevertheless, interestingly, כלאיים Kilayim is only דרבנן,
Derabbanan, ערלה, Orlah, which logically is linked in the תורה Torah to
נטע רבעי, Neta Reva'i, the fourth year fruits which are brought to
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and something that you might think is
more related to the קדושת הארץ, Kedushat Ha'aretz, that's something that we
say is הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha LeMoshe MiSinai. So those are two
things that apply outside the land of Israel. Now, the fact that
even though they're land-based, now the fact that it mentions something that's
rabbinic and it says oh, but it applies out of the land
of Israel suggests that
everything else
doesn't apply out of the land of Israel even at a דרבנן
Derabbanan level, which is important. And I'll discuss that in a minute.
רבי אליעזר אומר אף חדש, Rabbi Eliezer omer af Chadash, even חדש,
Chadash, very relevant now, it's going to be פסח Pesach very soon,
במהרה בימינו, Bimhera beyameinu, and the new prohibition of the new grain
that is prohibited until the 16th of ניסן, Nissan, that even though
that is based on the land, that applies also outside of the
land of Israel. So I want to read sort of a little
bit of גמרא Gemara that just clarifies sort of פשט Peshat of
this and then discuss a little bit some important points that come
up in this large תוספות Tosafot on the bottom of ל"ו עמוד
ב'. Lamed Vav Amud Bet. Let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. מאי תלויה ומאי שאינה תלויה, Mai teluya u'mai she'eina teluya, what
does it mean dependent and not dependent on the land? אי נימא
תלויה דכתיב בה ביאה, Iy eima teluya deketiv bah bia, if you
say dependent means the way the verse relates to its dependency on
the land, ושאינה תלויה דלא כתיב בה ביאה, Veshe'eina teluya delo ketiv
bah bia, and not dependent means when it does not say when
you enter the land. So a lot of verses, particularly in דברים,
Devarim, will say והיה כי תבוא אל הארץ, Vehaya ki tavo el
ha'aretz, it will be when you come to the land that God
gives you and you inherit it and A, B, and C happens.
So maybe it means when the תורה Torah connects certain מצוות Mitzvot
to entering into the land, so the תורה Torah makes it dependent
not on the dirt, but on entering the land, then it's limited
to the land of Israel. When the תורה Torah does not make
it dependent on entering into the land, it's not dependent. Okay, so
what would be with that? So the גמרא Gemara says ומאי אינה
תלויה? Umai eina teluya? So it says ושאינה תלויה שלא כתיב בה
ביאה, Veshe'eina teluya shelo ketiv bah bia, does not say when you
enter in the land. והרי תפילין ופטר חמור, Vaharei Tefillin u'Peter Chamor,
how about תפילין Tefillin and the firstborn of the donkey,
דכתיב בהן ביאה, Dekektiv bahen bia, it says in them entering. Entering
into the land, that's actually in
שמות. Shemos. והיה כי יביאך ה' אל ארץ הכנעני כאשר נשבע לך
ולאבותיך ונתנה לך, Vehayah ki yeviacha Hashem el eretz hakenani kaasher nishba
lecha uleavosecha unesana lach, whatever. What's the פסוק pasuk there?
Okay, 13:13, thank you.
Could open the סידור. siddur. That's true. People say it after they
put on their תפילין. tefillin.
Okay. והיה כי יביאך ה' אל ארץ הכנעני כאשר נשבע לך ולאבותיך
ונתנה לך והעברת כל פטר רחם לה' וכל פטר שגר בהמה אשר
יהיה לך הזכרים לה' וכל פטר חמור תפדה בשה ואם לא תפדה
וערפתו והיה כי ישאלך בנך מחר לאמר מה זאת ואמרת אליו,
Vehayah ki yeviacha Hashem el eretz hakenani kaasher nishba lecha uleavosecha unesana
lach vehaavarta kol peter rechem l’Hashem vekol peter sheger behemah asher yiheyeh
lecha hazcharim l’Hashem vekol peter chamor tifdeh beseh veim lo tifdeh vaarafto
vehayah ki yishalcha bincha machar lemor
mah zos veamarta elav, there we go, one of the פסוקים psukim
quoted for the מצוה mitzvah of הגדה, Haggadah, בחוזק יד הוציאנו ה'
ממצרים מבית עבדים והיה
לאות על ידך ולטוטפת בין עיניך כי בחוזק יד הוציאנו ה' ממצרים.
bechozek yad hotzianu Hashem mimitzrayim mibeis avadim vehayah leos al yadecha uletotafos
bein einecha ki bechozek yad hotzianu Hashem mimitzrayim. Okay, so maybe the
מצוה mitzvah of בכור bechor and פטר חמור peter chamor and תפילין
tefillin should be limited to what is it, to when we, to
only in the ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Maybe outside ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael it's only
דרבנן derabbanan or something. So actually, so the גמרא Gemara says, but
that can't be, the גמרא Gemara says ותפילין ופטר חמור, v’tefillin u’peter
chamor, wait one minute, ותפילין ופטר חמור דכתיב בהן ביאה ונוהגים בין
בארץ בין בחוץ לארץ. v’tefillin u’peter chamor deksiv bahen bi’ah v’nohagim bein
ba’aretz bein b’chutz la’aretz.
So how do we know that תפילין tefillin applies in חוץ לארץ?
chutz la’aretz? So if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says,
oh
because I was
thinking, תפילין, tefillin, one minute, אשכחן בכמה דוכתא ברבנן אמוראי דבבל דמנחי
תפילין. ashkechan b’chama duchsah b’rabbanan amorai d’Bavel d’manchi tefillin. Yeah, we know
that in בבל Bavel they would put on תפילין. tefillin. I mean
we see it in the גמרא. Gemara. Presumably the authors of the
בבלי Bavli knew that we wear תפילין tefillin in חוץ לארץ. chutz
la’aretz. And תוספות Tosafot says, well okay, but maybe that's only דרבנן.
derabbanan. Okay. So he says no, because the משנה Mishna makes it
clear that when we're talking we're talking even about rabbinically, right? Because
when the משנה Mishna mentions the exception of ערלה Orlah and כלאיים
Kilayim that applies in חוץ לארץ. chutz la’aretz. So כלאיים Kilayim is
only דרבנן derabbanan applying in חוץ לארץ. chutz la’aretz. So where what
we say that they don't apply in חוץ לארץ, chutz la’aretz, we
mean they don't apply whether biblically or rabbinically. So and we know
that תפילין tefillin does apply in חוץ לארץ, chutz la’aretz, even if
you wanted to argue rabbinically, it still doesn't fit the משנה. Mishna.
So therefore it cannot be that that means about whether the פסוק
pasuk links it to entering into the land or not. Now I
do want to say something, one minute, about תפילין tefillin being linked
to entering into the land, because there is a famous רש"י Rashi
on the תורה Torah that the רמב"ן Ramban actually picks up, רש"י
Rashi is actually quoting a מדרש הלכה Midrash Halacha about this, where,
where the פסוק pasuk is by the קריאת שמע, Kriyas Shema, where
it says, let me find the
פסוק, pasuk, 12:1, hold on,
we'll get to that.
We'll get to that. Okay. So the פסוק pasuk by קריאת שמע
Kriyas Shema is, hold on,
12:1, hold on,
I think it's in the second פרשה parsha of קריאת שמע. Kriyas
Shema.
Hold
on, 12:1, hold
on, no, the first פרשה parsha is, let me just check רש"י,
Rashi,
hold on,
yeah, exactly, hold on,
right. I don't find, one minute. We're going to go on, I'll
just tell it to you from memory. But hold on one second.
Hey, רש"י Rashi
stay here in France, he's saying.
Well,
he's saying how the גמרא Gemara knew. How the גמרא Gemara knew,
it's been some time, yeah.
Okay,
one minute.
Here, go. Hold on.
Okay, anyway, there's a רש"י Rashi which I'm not finding right now,
apologize, I should have looked it
up last night. Oh
yes,
here, רש"י, Rashi, but on the פסוק pasuk of שמע, Shema, this
is not on י"א י"ח Yud-Aleph Yud-Chet in דברים. Devarim. ושמתם את
דברי אלה על לבבכם ועל נפשכם, Vesamtem es devarai eileh al levavchem
ve'al nafshechem,
right?
Everybody with me, right? The פסוק pasuk ושמתם את דברי אלה על
לבבכם ועל נפשכם וקשרתם אתם לאות על ידכם והיו לטטפת בין עיניכם.
Vesamtem es devarai eileh al levavchem ve'al nafshechem uksfartem osam le'os al
yedchem vehayu letotafos bein eineichem. So רש"י Rashi says, what's ושמתם את
דברי אלה? Vesamtem es devarai eileh? אף לאחר שתגלו, Af acharei shetiglu,
because it speaks about you'll sin and you know, you'll go into
exile, you in the second פרשה parsha of שמע. Shema. היו מצוינים
במצוות, Heyu metzuyanim bemitzvot, הניחו תפילין, hinihu tefillin, עשו מזוזות, asu mezuzot,
to
you know, distinguish yourself out in גלות Galus with מצוות, mitzvot, תפילין
tefillin and מזוזה, mezuzah, כדי שלא יהיו לכם חדשים כשתחזרו, kedei shelo
yihyu lachem chadashim keshetachzoru,
so it shouldn't be like something new when you return to the
land. וכן הוא אומר הציבי לך ציונים. Vechein hu omer hatzivi lach
tziyunim. So the רמב"ן Ramban says, what do you mean it's practice?
It's a מצוה חיובית בגוף, mitzvah chuyah beguf, right? So this leads
the רמב"ן Ramban to lay out his whole theology that even the
מצוות התלויות בגוף mitzvot hateluyot beguf are fundamentally the real performance of
the מצוות mitzvot that the תורה—I Torah mean, which is true in
the תורה. Torah. The תורה Torah imagines—the תורה Torah doesn't lay out
an idea of a sort of a Judaism as a religion and
by the way, there's also the idea of living in the ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, right? In דברים, Devarim, it's basically these are the
מצוות mitzvot of the land, you live as a nation as a
people in the land. גלות Galus is called exile for a reason
because it's not the natural state of being. So the רמב"ן Ramban
says even when it's true that מצוות התלויות בגוף mitzvot hateluyot beguf
apply in חוץ לארץ, Chutz La'aretz, that's not really their ideal performance
and really the real way the תורה Torah wants you to be
performing all the מצוות mitzvot is in the ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
Now some people are so bothered that by this רש"י Rashi that
he talks about תפילין tefillin and מזוזות mezuzot that they're only like
practice for getting back into the land, that they switch the גרסא,
girsa, because when רש"י Rashi says תפילין ומזוזות, tefillin umezuzot, some people
want to claim—it's not true—but some people want to claim that רש"י
Rashi wrote this originally.
And people say it's תרומות ומעשרות, Terumos uMaasros, I
guess instead of תפילין ומזוזות, tefillin umezuzot, but it's not true. And
רש"י Rashi is actually picking up on the פסוקים pesukim because the
פסוקים pesukim speak about right? That you'll go into גלות, Galus, right?
Right it says אבדתם מהרה מעל הארץ הטובה avadtem maheira me'al ha'aretz
hatovah and then it says ושמתם את דברי אלה וקשרתם לאות על
ידכם ולמדתם את בניכם וכתבתם על מזוזות ביתך, vesamtem es devarai eileh
uksfartem le'os al yedchem velimadetem es beneichem uksfartem al mezuzos beiseicha, right?
למען ירבו ימיכם על הארץ lema'an yirbu yemeichem al ha'aretz exactly, על
האדמה al ha'adamah excuse me אשר נשבע ה' לאבותיכם. asher nishba Hashem
la'avoseichem.
So that really it's an important—it's like on one way you read
this גמרא Gemara and say what a crazy הוה אמינא havah amina
that תפילין tefillin you know should apply should not apply outside of
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, but you know רש"י Rashi there is that
רש"י Rashi is pointing to the fact that that's actually the פשט
pshat of the פסוקים pesukim and that all the מצוות mitzvot ultimately
are to be done in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. But okay, למעשה
lema'aseh it is true that when we are in גלות Galus we
still do these other מצוות mitzvot and what about פטר חמור? Peter
Chamor? Alright, I don't know, פטר חמור, Peter Chamor, but at least
to
read the תורה Torah מצוות mitzvot as a גאולה?
geulah? Oh, all תורה Torah מצוות, mitzvot, that's true too. Anyway, but
that doesn't make רש"י Rashi less—anyway, so the point is, is that
clearly תפילין tefillin and מזו—תפילין tefillin applies outside of Israel. So it
cannot be that the תלויה בארץ teluyah ba'aretz means that the פסוק
pasuk speaks about entering the land because then תפילין tefillin would not
apply in חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz. So the גמרא Gemara says,
אמר רב יהודה הכי קאמר, Amar Rav Yehuda hachi kama,
here's how to read it. כל מצוה שהיא חובת הגוף נוהגת בין
בארץ בין בחוץ לארץ. kol mitzvah shehi chovat haguf noheget bein ba'aretz
bein bechutz la'aretz. It's not about the way the פסוק pasuk frames
it. It's about the very nature of the מצוה mitzvah itself. If
it is something that is about you to do, you know, what
you as a person are supposed to do, then that applies everywhere.
חובת קרקע, chovat karka, if it relates to the to the earth,
right, so to the—to the—אינו נוהגת אלא בארץ eino noheget ela ba'aretz
and that's only in the land of Israel. So anything basically... except
for ערלה Orlah and כלאים Kilayim which is even in חוץ לארץ.
Chutz La'aretz. But anything basically... so you don't have to look in
the פסוקים, pesukim, you just look at the reality. Is this something
that deals with the land and the produce that emerges from the
land? Then it's in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. If it's unrelated to
the land and its produce, it relates even in חוץ לארץ. Chutz
La'aretz. Okay. And now the גמרא Gemara is going to say מנא
הני מילי? minani milei? How do you know this from? דתנו רבנן,
detanu rabbanan, our Rabbis taught: אלה החקים והמשפטים אשר תשמרון לעשות בארץ,
eileh hachukim vehamishpatim asher tishmerun la'asos ba'aretz,
that's the end of the פסוק. pasuk. So these are the laws,
אלה המדרשות, eileh hamidrashot, that's a very interesting gloss on the word
חוקים, chukim, normally you assume it to mean like you know not
civil law, maybe it's opposed to משפטים mishpatim which is civil law,
or maybe it's something which seems relatively arbitrary. I don't know... מדרש
הלכה. Midrash Halacha.
I understand, but it's very interesting because it's speaking about observing these
in the land and I'm not exactly sure what the link is
between the word חוק chok and מדרשות midrashot even if מדרשות midrashot
means מדרש הלכה Midrash Halacha and not מדרש אגדה, Midrash Aggada, right?
But you don't observe the מדרש, Midrash, you observe the הלכה. Halacha.
So it's I don't know... if you're seeing any interesting interpretations there
in your English. But to me it's a very strange gloss on
that. והמשפטים, vehamishpatim, the laws, אלה הדינים, eileh hadinim, these are like
the civil law. אשר תשמרון, asher tishmerun, that you should observe, זו
משנה, zo mishnah, that does not actually refer to the actual performance,
that refers actually to the learning of it, the teaching of the
laws in order that in order to observe. So maybe that's parallel
to חוקים, chukim, like the מדרש Midrash and the משנה. Mishnah. The
מדרש Midrash is,
what is it? David Weiss Halivni wrote a book, right? מדרש Midrash
and משנה. Mishnah. Like those are the two components of what תלמוד
תורה's Talmud Torah about. One is how do you derive it from
the פסוקים, pesukim, and the other is the teaching of the law
of the bottom line what's derived, not the process of derivation. Okay,
so maybe it's parallel to the חוקים chukim is the תשמרון, tishmerun,
so whether it's through the process of engaging the פסוקים pesukim or
the teaching of the law, that's how you preserve them and preserve
the engagement with them. ועשות, Va'asot, that you perform them, זו מעשה,
zu ma'aseh, that's the doing. בארץ, Ba'aretz, in the land. Okay, יכול
כל המצות כולן לא יהו נוהגות אלא בארץ, yakhol kol hamitzvot kulan
lo yehu nohagot ela ba'aretz, maybe all the מצות, mitzvot, אלו חוקים
אשר תשמרון לעשות בארץ, elu chukim asher tishmerun la'asot ba'aretz, right, all
of them only apply in the land, similar to what we've discussed
before. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, כל הימים אשר אתם חיים על האדמה,
kol hayamim asher atem chayim al ha'adamah, all the
all the years that you are living on the land.
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
I know, the irony here is that אשר אתם חיים על האדמה,
asher atem chayim al ha'adamah, but the גמרא Gemara is reading it
כל הימים, kol hayamim, so forever, so something that has universal application.
There's periods in our history where we weren't dwelling on the land,
so that must mean that the מצות mitzvot apply again, we're learning
all places from a פסוק pasuk that's about all times. אי כל
הימים, I kol hayamim, if it's all times, יכול יהו נוהגים בין
בארץ בין בחוץ לארץ, yakhol yehu nohagim bein ba'aretz bein b'chutz la'aretz,
maybe every single applies outside of the land of Israel as well.
תלמוד לומר בארץ, Talmud lomar ba'aretz, no, it emphasizes in the land.
אחרי שריבה הכתוב ומיעט, Acharei sheriba hakatuv u'mi'et, after it spoke broadly
and it spoke narrowly, which one what applies everyone, what applies only
in the land? צא ולמד, Tzei u'lemad, מה ביקש לבן הארמי, mah
bikaish Lavan ha'Arami, very appropriate timing for צא ולמד Tzei u'lemad גמרא.
Gemara. צא ולמד, Tzei u'lemad, go out and look, ממה שאמר בענין,
mi'mah she'amar b'inyan, אבד תאבדון, abeit avadun, after that opening it says
destroy את כל המקומות אשר עבדו שם הגוים את אלהיהם, et kol
hamakomot asher avdu sham hagoyim et eloheihem, all the places they worship
their idols. מה עבודת כוכבים מיוחדת שחובת הגוף, mah avodat kokhavim yuchedet
she'hovat haguf, the same way destroying עבודת כוכבים avodat kokhavim is something
that is a personal obligation, or not worshipping them and also destroying
I assume, so נוהגת nohagesh בין בארץ בין בחוץ לארץ, bein ba'aretz
bein b'chutz la'aretz, and therefore that applies out in all places. אף
כל שחובת הגוף af kol she'hovat haguf נוהגת nohagesh בין בארץ בין
בחוץ לארץ. bein ba'aretz bein b'chutz la'aretz. Everything similar. So we are
reading the end of the פסוק, pasuk, כל הימים אשר אתם חיים
על האדמה, kol hayamim asher atem chayim al ha'adamah, which again, ironically
because we're bracketing על האדמה al ha'adamah and we're reading כל הימים,
kol hayamim, and the immediate next פסוק pasuk after כל הימים kol
hayamim is destroying עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So we use that as
the paradigm and say anything that is like עבודה זרה, avodah zarah,
the not worshipping, the destroying עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, etc. applies in
all times and all places, anything that's a חובת הגוף. hovat haguf.
Again, the irony here besides just that it says על האדמה, al
ha'adamah, the additional irony is that the מצוה mitzvah to destroy עבודה
זרה avodah zarah at one level it applies even in חוץ לארץ,
chutz la'aretz, but there's a heightened obligation in the land. The גמרא
Gemara says in the ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael חייב אתה לשרש אחריה,
hayyav attah lishreish achareiha,
you have to go and like uproot it, like dig after the
roots, you have to completely uproot it in the land. Right, and
that's certainly the sense of the פסוקים. pesukim. The פסוקים, pesukim, you
read the פסוקים, pesukim, you do not get a sense that if
you happen to be visiting somewhere in India and see an idol
you're supposed to break it. Right, the sense is that when you're
settling in the land, that this should be your land, you have
to destroy all the עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So that raises another
interesting question of what תלויה בארץ t'luya ba'aretz means, because that's not
about קרקע, karka, that's about being in the place that is your
nation. And we're going to see other מצות mitzvot that are related
to that. I don't know, building a בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, having
a מלך, melekh, there are a lot of things that are setting
up ערי מקלט, arei miklat, right, there are a lot of things
that have to do with the fact of what it means that
this is our our country, right, which is all which is a
very different type of תלויה בארץ t'luya ba'aretz that also applies in
the land. And so the irony here is that destroying עבודה זרה
avodah zarah is similar to that. I mean there is a מצוה
mitzvah outside, but the real מצוה mitzvah is in the land of
Israel. So again it's very funny that this serves as this model
for חובת הגוף hovat haguf that applies everywhere.
So is there an obligation to break that idol in India?
Yeah, I think like when it comes into your possession or whatever,
but you don't have to proactively go after it. Yeah, the irony,
the double irony is that you read all of מסכת עבודה זרה,
Masechet Avodah Zarah, and I mean scholars, academics have written on this.
You read all of מסכת עבודה זרה Masechet Avodah Zarah and you
would never have an idea that there's a מצוה mitzvah to destroy
עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, because there was a historical reality that the
Jews then living in under Roman rule or whatever they had to
basically completely bracket the מצוה mitzvah to destroy עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
So, yes.
Is there anything to say that the verb here that's operative is
נוהג, nohag, and so there you see that implicit in the word
מנהג minhag is very close to הלכה halakhah and חובה?
hovah? Well, I think נוהג nohag means applicable. Look, you're right, I
mean Chaim Soloveitchik has spoken about the fact that you have that
this distinction is captured in modern Hebrew where we talk about a
difference between מנהג minhag and נוהג. nohag. מנהג minhag is a custom,
נוהג nohag is practice. So, the problem is that we wind up
conflating the two. But the simple sense of נוהג nohag here means
is applicable, right. It's practice. Okay. חוץ מן הערלה והכלאים, Chutz min
ha'orlah ve'hakilayim, except for ערלה orlah and כלאים kilayim which apply even
in חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz as we said. One is ערלה הלכה
למשה מסיני orlah halakhah l'Moshe m'Sinai and כלאים kilayim is דרבנן. de'rabbanan.
איבעיא ibayei and then Rabbi Eliezer says, and this is... It is
also so important, especially now that we're coming up to פסח, Pesach,
well actually it's less immediate, now that we're coming up to פסח
Pesach it's going to be less important, it's important for the half
of the year from ראש השנה Rosh Hashana until פסח. Pesach. Anyway,
whether חדש Chadash applies outside the land of Israel.
So איבעיא להו, Ibaylu, רבי
אליעזר
Rabbi
Eliezer
לכולא פליג lekula palig what? חדש! Chadash! What'd I say? חוץ? Chutz?
I'm sorry. חדש Chadash applies from, right, because usually just to sort
of so people don't know what happens is is that in the
land of Israel there's really only one wheat season. So the prohibition
of חדש Chadash has almost no real impact because by the time
the wheat becomes like ready to be harvested, I mean the first
stuff that's harvested is right around פסח Pesach and that's really the
only harvest. So therefore, right, חדש Chadash means anything that is harvested
before the עומר Omer is brought is forbidden to be eaten until
the עומר Omer is brought. But in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael you'd
really have to go out of your way to harvest wheat and
have it ready to be eaten like before the עומר, Omer, because
the עומר Omer is like the barley is the earliest harvest and
so on, and then there would that would be the only wheat
harvest. But in חוץ לארץ, Chutz La'aretz, and you know, what?
Yeah, winter wheat.
Yeah, winter wheat, which gets harvested right around, you know, after the,
you know, the עומר Omer and,
and then, I'm sorry, which gets harvested before the next, I'm sorry,
right, right, so because the difference, let me clarify, the stuff that
gets harvested after the עומר Omer it has to do with when
it takes root. So everything that is and all the wheat and
barley that you're going to harvest that year in Israel has taken
root before the עומר Omer is brought and then when the עומר
Omer is brought then you harvest it, it's totally okay. But what
happens is is that in חוץ לארץ, Chutz La'aretz, not only in
the states but in, you know, France, in Germany and all those
places, you know, wheat would take root, would be planted and take
root, you know, in the winter and it would be harvested sometime
in the, well no actually when would it be harvested? It would
be harvested because I think it comes to market right around ראש
השנה Rosh Hashana time. So why is it called winter wheat? I
think it's the spring wheat that's the problem, not the winter wheat.
The winter wheat is what you harvest in the spring. Okay, I
might get the names wrong, but anyway what happens is I think
this might be the spring wheat. Anyway it's planted, it's planted after,
like in the spring, and it's harvested like sometime in the fall
and it comes, or like you know at, or in the summer
and it comes to market right around ראש השנה Rosh Hashana time.
It was planted after the עומר Omer and it's harvested, you know,
somewhere at and, and comes to market right around ראש השנה Rosh
Hashana time. So if you were practicing out of Israel the law
of חדש, Chadash, you can't eat any of that wheat for the
next six months. Okay, and therefore it becomes a really major issue
that the ראשונים Rishonim had to confront. And the question is, well
first of all which wheat are you dealing with? Are you dealing
with the stuff that was just recently harvested or the stuff that
was, you know, that was sort of already growing or whatever in
the springtime when the עומר Omer was planted, and when the עומר
Omer was harvested, how do you know? So it becomes a very
big question about חדש Chadash in חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz. So let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. חוץ מן הערלה והכלאים. chutz min
ha'orlah vehakilayim. איבעיא להו, Ibaylu, there is the question. רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer לכולא פליג, lekula palig, when רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer arguing leniently או לחומרא פליג, o lechumra palig, or
strictly? What does that mean? לחומרא פליג, lechumra palig, he's being strict
and he's saying that חדש Chadash applies in חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz.
הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma,
חוץ מן הערלה והכלאים, chutz min ha'orlah vehakilayim, תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
is saying only ערלה orlah and כלאים kilayim apply in חוץ לארץ,
Chutz La'aretz, דהלכתא גמירי לה, dehilchesa gemiri la,
this גמרא gemara here frames them both as הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha
lemoshe misinai. אף על גב דאיכא למימר חובת קרקע היא, af al
gav de'ika lemeimar chovas karka hi, although logically these are land-bound מצוות,
mitzvot, nevertheless ערלה orlah and כלאים kilayim apply in חוץ לארץ, Chutz
La'aretz, אבל חדש בארץ אין בחוץ לארץ לא. aval Chadash ba'aretz in
bechutz la'aretz lo. חדש Chadash though is only in the land. מאי
טעמא? mai ta'ama? מושב לאחר ירושה וישיבה משמע, moshav leachar yerusha veyeshiva
mashma,
because here's what it says by חדש, Chadash, it speaks about when
you come to the land and then it says בכל מושבתיכם. bechol
moshvotechem. What's the פסוק? pasuk?
By the way he's not arguing with me, he's disagreeing with the
תנא קמא.
Tanna Kamma. No, no, no, he's disagreeing, one minute, we're not up
to what he said yet. Let's first say what the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma says. Okay, it says, the
פסוק pasuk says לחם וקלי וכרמל לא תאכלו עד עצם היום הזה
עד הביאכם את קרבן אלהיכם חקת עולם לדרתיכם בכל מושבתיכם.
lechem vekali vekarmel lo tochlu ad etzem hayom hazeh ad havi'achem et
korban eloheichem chukat
olam ledoroteichem bechol moshvotechem.
All of your places where
you dwell. So all of places
where you dwell could be understood to mean חוץ לארץ, Chutz La'aretz,
or בכל מושבתיכם bechol moshvotechem could mean, well okay,
in חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz. So that's going to be the debate.
So one minute. So תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says חדש Chadash is
only in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Okay, אבל חדש בארץ אין בחוץ
לארץ לא. aval Chadash ba'aretz in bechutz la'aretz lo. מאי טעמא mai
ta'ama why? מושב moshav when it says where you dwell that doesn't
mean anywhere, it means לאחר ירושה וישיבה משמע. leachar yerusha veyeshiva mashma.
It means after you're settled in the land. So the first fourteen
years they entered the land and they were fighting the wars and
they were conquering the land, they wouldn't have been חייב chayiv in
חדש Chadash because it wasn't yet מושב, moshav, like they weren't yet
settled in the land. So בכל מושבתיכם bechol moshvotechem means after you're
settled in the land, but it does not mean anywhere you dwell.
Okay, that would be תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. ואתא רבי אליעזר למימר,
ve'ata Rabbi Eliezer lemeimar, and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer comes to say
אף על גב. af al gav.
Even חדש chadash applies outside of the land of
Israel. מאי טעמא mai ta'ama מושב, moshav, when it says where you
dwell, בכל מקום שאתם יושבים, bechol makom she'atem yoshvim, wherever you dwell.
So he, that's the simple read of the משנה, mishna, that he's
being strict and he's saying not only do those two apply in
חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, even חדש chadash applies in חוץ לארץ. chutz
la'aretz. Okay, so that would be one way to read it. או
דלמא, o dilma, or do we say לכולא פליג, lekula palig, he's
being lenient, והכי קאמר, vehachi ka'amar, תנא קמא, tanna kamma, חוץ מן
הערלה וכלאים chutz min ha'orlah vechilayim דהלכתא גמירי לה, dehilchata gemiri lah,
the things that apply in חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, the land-based things
are ערלה orlah and כלאים, kilayim, that we have as a הלכה
למשה מסיני, halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai,
וכל שכן חדש, vechol sheken chadash, and certainly חדש. chadash. דמושב בכל
מקום שאתם יושבים משמע.
demoshav
bechol makom she'atem yoshvim mashma.
That goes without saying. It says בכל מושבותיכם, bechol moshvoteichem, I don't
even have to say that. Okay, it's very funny. Like you know,
ואתא רבי אליעזר למימר,
ve'ata
Rabi
Eliezer lemeymar, Rabi Eliezer says no, you're wrong. חדש אינו נוהג אלא
בארץ. chadash eino noheg ela ba'aretz.
חדש chadash is only in the land. דמושב לאחר ירושה וישיבה משמע.
demoshav le'acher yerusha viyishiva mashma. מושב moshav means after your dwelling, but
it means in the land. ומאי אף? umai af? So why does
he say even? אקמייתא. akamayta. No, no, no. Even חדש chadash is
limited to the land of Israel. It's a really עיקר חסר מן
הספר. ikar chaser min hasefer. How could he be responding to a
חדש chadash of the תנא קמא tanna kamma that the תנא קמא
tanna kamma didn't say? Anyway, the גמרא Gemara thankfully is going to
reject that. It's going to have רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer being the
מחמיר. machmir. תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear, דאמר אביי, de'amar
Abaye, מאן תנא דפליג עליה דרבי אליעזר? man tanna dipalig alei de-Rabi
Eliezer? Who argues on רבי אליעזר? Rabi Eliezer?
תנא קמא? tanna kamma?
What, who is the תנא קמא? tanna kamma? Yes. רבי ישמעאל. Rabi
Yishmael. It's רבי ישמעאל. Rabi Yishmael. דתניא, detanya, ללמדך שכל מקום שנאמר
בו מושב אינו אלא לאחר ירושה וישיבה. lelamedcha shechol makom shene'emar bo
moshav eino ela le'acher yerusha viyishiva.
So here we're going to get to a general hermeneutic about how
to read the פסוק pasuk מושבותיכם. moshvoteichem.
Does it mean wherever you dwell, even out of the land of
Israel, or does it mean after you've settled in the land? So
this is going to be a position, a debate of רבי ישמעאל
Rabi Yishmael and רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva about something which seems much
more like, not as central to sort of this issue, but it's
the question about when did they bring נסכים, nesachim, the sort of
wine and flour and oil that would accompany קרבנות. korbanot. Because there
the פסוקים pesukim speak about that you should bring it. The פסוק
pasuk is, what's the פסוק? pasuk? אשה להשם. isha l'Hashem.
Right. So the פסוק pasuk is in שלח לך, Shelach Lecha, כי
תבואו אל ארץ מושבותיכם ועשיתם אשה להשם. ki tavo'u el eretz moshvoteichem
va'asitem isha l'Hashem. The land of מושבותיכם. moshvoteichem. Now I have to
tell you, you ask me, there's a slight difference between בכל מושבותיכם
bechol moshvoteichem and ארץ מושבותיכם. eretz moshvoteichem. Okay, but anyway, רבי ישמעאל
Rabi Yishmael says that the פסוקים pesukim there are that you only
bring נסכים nesachim at a במה גדולה. bamah gedolah. במה גדולה bamah
gedolah means that there's a central altar. So there's a period where
they would, there would be היתר במות, heter bamot, you could offer
on your private במה, bamah, but there would still be a central
communal altar like in נוב Nov and גבעון Givon and in גלגל
Gilgal and שילה, Shilo, whatever, there would be a central altar, a
במה גדולה. bamah gedolah. So רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer says that since
it says in the plural, you shall bring the נסכים, nesachim, okay,
לכם lachem etc., that it's in the plural, that it means only
on the במה גדולה. bamah gedolah. So if it's only on the
במה גדולה, bamah gedolah, so then what does it mean when it
says, you know, wherever you dwell because ארץ מושבותיכם? eretz moshvoteichem? It
can't mean, forget even חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, does it mean throughout
the land of Israel? So he said, well, how could you bring
נסכים nesachim throughout the land of Israel if you can only bring
it in one central place? So מושבותיכם moshvoteichem can't mean throughout the
land of Israel. The only thing מושבותיכם moshvoteichem can mean is after
you settle in the land. Okay, everybody with me? If it means
the central במה, bamah, then מושבותיכם moshvoteichem can't mean wherever you are,
it has to mean after you settle in the land. That's what
he says. So therefore the first 14 years they would not bring
נסכים. nesachim. So the גמרא Gemara says, ללמדכם, lelamedchem, this teaches you,
once I start with the assumption that you would only bring it
on a במה גדולה bamah gedolah because it's in the
plural, לכם, lachem, I'm giving it to you as a communal, as
a whole, and therefore it's only the במה גדולה, bamah gedolah, then
מושבותיכם moshvoteichem can't mean wherever you are, מושבותיכם moshvoteichem must mean after
you settled in the land, after the first 14 years. And this
teaches you שכל מקום שנאמר בו מושב, shechol makom shene'emar bo moshav,
whenever it says מושב, moshav, אינו אלא לאחר ירושה וישיבה, eino ela
le'acher yerusha viyishiva, does not mean wherever you dwell, it means after
you've settled. דברי רבי ישמעאל. divrei Rabi Yishmael. That's what רבי ישמעאל
Rabi Yishmael said. אמר לו רבי עקיבא, amar lo Rabi Akiva, רבי
עקיבא Rabi Akiva says to him, הרי שבת שנאמר בו מושבות. harei
Shabbat shene'emar bo moshvot. It says by שבת, Shabbat, מושבות. moshvot. רש"י
Rashi says לא תבערו אש בכל מושבותיכם. lo teva'aru esh bechol moshvoteichem.
No, it says a different פסוק. pasuk. The פסוק pasuk that says
שבת היא להשם בכל מושבותיכם. Shabbat hi l'Hashem bechol moshvoteichem. So there
it says בכל מושבותיכם, bechol moshvoteichem, ונוהגת בין בארץ בין בחוץ לארץ.
venoheget bein ba'aretz bein bechutz la'aretz. That means clearly wherever you dwell.
So מושבות moshvot does not mean after you settle, מושבות moshvot means
wherever you dwell. אמר לו, amar lo, שבת קל וחומר אתיא. Shabbat
kal vachomer atya. Nah, that we know from a קל וחומר. kal
vachomer. מה מצות קלות נוהגות בין בארץ בין בחוץ לארץ, mah mitzvot
kalot nohagot bein ba'aretz bein bechutz la'aretz, if other sort of trivial
mitzvot, not trivial חס ושלום, chas veshalom, if other lighter מצות mitzvot
apply in חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, and presumably it means that are
not dependent on the land of Israel, the light מצות mitzvot that
are not dependent on the land apply in חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz,
שבת חמורה לא כל שכן? Shabbat chamura lo kol sheken? How much
more so the weightier מצוה mitzvah of שבת? Shabbat? Okay, so therefore,
so then we still have to answer why does it say מושבות
moshvos by שבת, Shabbos, but we'll get to that later. Anyway, what
you have here is a debate of רבי ישמעאל Rebbe Yishmael and
רבי עקיבא, Rebbe Akiva, that רבי ישמעאל Rebbe Yishmael says מושבות moshvos
means in the land of Israel after you've settled, although there are
some times when it means something else like שבת Shabbos and we'll
have to deal with it, but it means in the land of
Israel after you've settled, and רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva says the default
meaning of מושבות moshvos is wherever you dwell. So now apply that
to the חדש chadash debate, and therefore the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
that says that it's only in the land follows רבי ישמעאל Rebbe
Yishmael that says מושבות moshvos means in the land when you've settled
it, and רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer that says that applies everywhere follows
רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva that מושבות moshvos means wherever you dwell. Yes,
Michael.
So how come—I asked this before—why can't we say it means even
עבר הירדן Ever HaYarden and not the rest of חוץ לארץ? Chutz
La'aretz? Because you might think it's different because ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
proper was supposed to
be—the general presumption is that עבר הירדן Ever HaYarden has the same
קדושה kedusha of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and you don't need a
special פסוק pasuk to include it. There are some places in which
עבר הירדן Ever HaYarden has a slightly different status, like by ביכורים
bikkurim or whatever, but the general presumption is, I mean, the basic—if
you see a basic ריבוי ribbuy of the פסוק, pasuk, it's not
to outside of the land, it's to include broader חוץ לארץ. Chutz
La'aretz. That's the basic assumption חז"ל Chazal make that they work with
the presumption that עבר הירדן Ever HaYarden generally is—has קדושת ארץ ישראל
kedushas Eretz Yisrael and is already primarily included already in the land,
so you wouldn't need a ריבוי. ribbuy. I hear the question, I'm
just telling you that's the... yeah.
So what do you say to רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva therefore today
we're still not settled in the land because there's no national central
במה? bama? What? In other words,
what's the definition of the completion of the settlement?
Oh, that's fourteen—that's the first fourteen years. You don't mean רבי עקיבא,
Rebbe Akiva, you mean רבי ישמעאל. Rebbe Yishmael. רבי ישמעאל Rebbe Yishmael
says that it only applied
after—right, that would be after the first fourteen years of conquering the
land.
And then there was a central altar? Yes.
Well,
no, no, no, there was a central altar beforehand. It's just that
the נסכים nesachim did not apply because it was not yet מושבותיכם.
moshvoseichem. That's his whole point. They could have been brought at the
central altar, but that's what the פסוק pasuk has to tell you,
that they don't begin until after the land has been conquered and
settled, until after the first fourteen.
So the fact that that central altar subsequently was destroyed is irrelevant,
the status has already been established.
Correct, correct. I mean, it would still be limited to when there
is a central altar—that's what I was gonna ask—yeah, yeah, but you
only—but it only begins after the first fourteen years. Right. So, okay,
now I want to talk about this big תוספות. Tosfos. Two important
points. I want to start with חדש chadash because it's very relevant
for us. Now first of all, the point is this תוספות Tosfos
כל מצוה. Kol Mitzva. So first he talks about ערלה, orlah, which
I'll get to in a minute, but I want to first talk
about the חדש, chadash, which is coming up and people feel like
has greater relevance. So the question is if we פוסקים—how pasken do
you פוסק? pasken? רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer says here it applies in
חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz. Do we פוסק pasken that way or not?
Okay. The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says that it doesn't, so maybe
we'll just go like the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. So the problem
is that there's another משנה. Mishna. The other משנה Mishna is, let
me pull it up...
so you're getting פסק p'sak now?
I am not giving פסק, p'sak, I am teaching הלכה. halakha.
So you're saying חדש chadash applies חוץ לארץ? Chutz La'aretz?
Yeah, but you would say we should go like the תנא קמא,
Tanna Kamma, right? That would make life easy. And according to the
תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, remember תוספות Tosfos pointed out that it's—that if
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says it doesn't apply in חוץ לארץ,
Chutz La'aretz, then that means it doesn't apply even דרבנן, d'rabbanan, because
the משנה Mishna is including things that are דרבנן. d'rabbanan. So that
would be like the best in terms of—what?
I only ask about the הלכה. halakha.
So there you go. Okay.
So
the טור Tur goes on for pages on this.
Okay. So anyway it says like
this... okay, here's the last משנה Mishna in ערלה. orlah. It says
like this: החדש אסור מן התורה בכל מקום. Hachadash asur min hatorah
bechol makom. See, that's where the חתם סופר Chasam Sofer gets his
line from, חדש אסור מן התורה. chadash asur min hatorah. It's a
משנה Mishna in ערלה. orlah. החדש אסור מן התורה בכל מקום, Hachadash
asur min hatorah bechol makom, והערלה הלכה והכלאים מדברי סופרים. veha'orlah halakha
vehakilayim midivrei sofrim. So it's got ערלה orlah and כלאים, kilayim, that's
either הלכה למשה מסיני halakha l'moshe misinai or מדברי סופרים. midivrei sofrim.
But חדש chadash בכל מקום bechol makom means דאורייתא d'oraisa בכל מקום,
bechol makom, and nobody debates it. So a number of ראשונים Rishonim
say, "Oh, let's just go like the משנה Mishna in קידושין Kiddushin
that has it as a דעת יחיד da'as yachid of רבי אליעזר
Rebbe Eliezer and we could say we פוסקים pasken like the תנא
קמא." Tanna Kamma. And others say you're not allowed to do that
because you've got another משנה Mishna that's a סתם משנה. stam Mishna.
Then it gets all questions about סתם ואחר כך מחלוקת, stam ve'achar
kach machlokes, but that's a סתם משנה stam Mishna that's situated in
the עיקר ikkar discussion of those issues in ערלה, orlah, so that
should dictate and that shows that it is the הלכה. halakha. So
there's that debate of do you פוסק—which pasken position do you פוסק?
pasken? If you look at תוספות, Tosfos, look at the bottom here
of תוספות Tosfos on the bottom of למד ו' עמוד ב'. lamed
vav amud beis. תוספות Tosfos says like this: ונראה, venira, the very
last line of the תוספות Tosfos of למד ו' עמוד ב', lamed
vav amud beis, ונראה דחדש נוהג בזמן הזה. venira dechadash noheig bizman
hazeh. Says ונראה, venira, okay? Here he doesn't enter into that discussion,
right? It's also a funny phrase,
בזמן הזה. bizman hazeh. What he really means is not a question
about when, but a question about outside the land of Israel. Although
somebody could argue, well, since it's תלוי talui in the bringing of
the עומר, omer, so maybe if there's no bringing of the עומר
omer it doesn't apply, but the גמרא Gemara is very clear about
that, that it's דאורייתא, d'oraisa, it doesn't matter whether there's... So תוספות
Tosafos by saying בזמן הזה, Bizman Hazeh, what he really more means
is in now, like out of Israel, for us. Okay. ולכך, Ul'kach,
although it's funny, just as ונראה, V'nirei, he doesn't get into that
discussion about do we פוסקין pasken רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, do we
פוסקין pasken תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. ולכך יש להיזהר שאם אדם יודע
בוודאי שהשעורים נזרעו אחר זמן הקרבת העומר, Ul'kach yesh lehizaher she-im adam
yode'a bevvaday she-se'orim nizre'u achar zman hakravas haomer, if you
know that the grains were planted definitely after the עומר Omer was
brought, דהיינו אחר ט"ז בניסן שלא יאכל מהם, deino achar tet-zayin b'Nisan
shelo yochal meihem, that you should not eat from them if you
know for sure that they were planted after. And this is שעורים,
Se'orim, I know, it's funny he mentions שעורים, Se'orim, it's everything, but
the reason he probably mentioned שעורים Se'orim is because a big area
which was to challenge was Mead, was the sort of
beer, and that therefore, and that was the stuff that was like
I think that they had, I forget at one time I knew
all the הלכה, halacha, all the history of this stuff. But anyway,
there were like a lot of beer that they couldn't do without
and that there was, they could not sort of להיזהר lehizaher in
terms of.
Use it as a business, right?
Or it's not אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. שלא יאכל מהם. Shelo yochal
meihem. ומספק אין לאסור כל השעורים, Umissafek ein le'asur kol hase'orim, we
shouldn't אסור assur everything out of ספק. safek. כיון דרוב שעורים נזרעו
קודם ט"ז בניסן, Keivan d'rov se'orim nizre'u kodem tet-zayin b'Nisan, you go
by the רוב. rov. So, it's so funny, it's like it is
an איסור דאורייתא, issur de-oraita, ספק safek wouldn't be enough, but there's
an assertion that the majority was beforehand. Okay, is that assertion really
true? Is there ways of knowing, is there a way of being
מבורר דאפשר אזלינן בתר רובא או ביטול ברוב? meva'rer d'efshar azlinan basar
ruba o bittul berov? It's a little bit of a question, which
it is, because there's a question that it's all mixed up or
the question is you don't know which lot it came from, but
you could assume that it comes from the רוב. rov. Anyway, they
basically started, most ראשונים Rishonim started with the reality that we're not
נזהר nizhar and let's find a way
to justify it and they sort of worked backwards. Okay. Until you
clarify this שעורים Se'orim he means חטה? Chita? No, that's what Michael
asked. I think, I mean, it would apply equally to wheat, but
the bigger issue I think had to do with the beer and
with therefore was barley. The beer was the big thing that was
very pervasive that they had to. How this applies to all things.
It applies to all things. Okay. ובירושלמי משמע נמי דחדש נוהג אף
בשל עובדי כוכבים, Uv'Yerushalmi mashma nami d'chadash noheig af beshel ovdei kochavim,
דפרכה לה דמתניתין דהא, diparcha lah d'masnisin d'ha, what about the fact
that the grain is grown by non-Jews? Maybe that should be a
way out of it. So you have all these suggestions. Maybe it
doesn't apply in חוץ לארץ, Chutz La'aretz, maybe it doesn't apply if
it's grown by non-Jews, okay, etc. No, that's not going to help
us. דפרכה לה דמתניתין דקתני אף החדש אמאי לא תני חלה משום
לפי שאינו בא בעובדי כוכבים. Diparcha lah d'masnisin diksani af hachadash amai
lo tani challah mishum lefi she-eino ba'ovdei kochavim. So the ירושלמי Yerushalmi
says why is something not listed and it says we're not talking
about things that are, that don't apply when they're owned by non-Jews.
משמע דחדש דקתני מתניתין נוהג בשל עובדי כוכבים. Mashma dechadash deksani masnisin
noheig beshel ovdei kochavim. It sounds like everything being discussed is things
that apply even if they're owned by non-Jews. So being grown by
non-Jews doesn't help, being grown in חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz doesn't help
if you פוסקין pasken like רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, and you have
to rely on an issue like רוב. rov. Then the question is,
is the
רוב rov really accurate and is the רוב rov really accurate under
some circumstances? Some cases maybe yes, some cases no. The big thing
also so some ראשונים Rishonim developed an idea called ספק ספיקא. s'fek
s'feka. The ספק ספיקא s'fek s'feka was the following.
Maybe the stuff came from last year's grain.
And even if it came from this year's grain, maybe it came
from the grain that took root before the עומר. Omer. Of course
the funny thing is that's really just one ספק, safek, maybe it's
from grain that's ישן yashan as opposed to grain that's חדש. chadash.
So, you have a lot and some ראשונים Rishonim try to say
we פוסקין pasken like רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, some try to say
we פוסקין pasken that it doesn't apply by non-Jews. The ערוך השולחן
Aruch Hashulchan if I remember correctly suggests that maybe it only applies
in the wheat season that could be הותר hutar by the עומר,
Omer, exactly the whole problem is because there is a second wheat
season, so like in a sense second wheat season, the grain is
never fit for being brought for the עומר, Omer, so therefore it
should never be אסור assur from חדש. chadash. I mean, drives any
חדש chadash out of? No, well, driving חדש chadash out of a
second wheat season, not out of the first one. Anyway, people try
to come up with justifications, but the clearest reality was that for
like a thousand years people were, the reality in the world in
which they lived, that they could not avoid eating it and they
started with that practice and they had to find justifications. Nowadays, nowadays,
I know, I understand. So nowadays there are definitely people that are
מחמיר machmir on חדש, chadash, especially it becomes harder because to rely
on some of these היתרים. heteirim. There was a time in my
life when I was מחמיר machmir on this, then it became hard
because there's somebody who for better or worse, it's sort of like
living in the world where you have
הכשרים hechsherim on the food, so therefore like nobody will ever eat
anything without an הכשר, hechsher, even if it's totally kosher once we
have access. So it's not exactly the same. But here somebody actually
did the research and now you can actually send away and for
two bucks or whatever they'll send you a little pamphlet and you
can go into the grocery store and basically based on the barcode
or based on whatever know exactly like which lot of wheat... You
know something came from and whether it came from חדש chadash or
ישן. yashan. So it's like you know to say well ספק ספיקא
sfek sefeka and רוב rov or whatever the information is available with
where you know where the wheat came from that's being used in
different types of products. So it really raises very serious questions you
know but the מנהג minhag had been the נוהג nohag had been
for a thousand years that we somehow became oblivious you know to
that איסור. issur. We the practice was we for again those realities
of what they was available to them in terms of the wheat
and the beer and whatever and then you had to find a
way of rationalizing it. Yes.
So it's when it's when
it took root is the salient.
Right. To take root before after the עומר. Omer. Right.
To my understanding if there is a way to find out then
how do you not?
It is hard to it is hard הלכתית halachically to justify it.
I mean what you could say is you could say the fact
that the practice had been for so long shows I don't know
if you went to shows that we פוסקים pasken like תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma against רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. That's the easiest thing to
say you know then you don't have to worry about ספק ספיקא
sfek sefeka and רוב rov and all those other things.
But what do you do with that other issue?
All right so סתם אחר כך מחלוקת stam achar kach machlokes or
something you know. I mean I don't know what to tell you.
I mean there's all I mean that's why if you want to
be מחמיר machmir on חדש. chadash. I'm really asking. Yeah I mean
it's a real issue. Let's talk about another thing where the practice
seemed to be against
what the
הלכה halacha
would have indicated which is the question about ערלה. orla. So if
ערלה orla applies in חוץ לארץ chutz l'aretz תוספות Tosafot wants to
know how do we drink the wine because all the wine comes
from the grafting of shoots of vines to you know old you
know to existing vines and that should make everything to be ערלה.
orla. So if you take a look at תוספות. Tosafot. Wait because
the new one makes it new? If you take a right if
you take a branch off of one vine and graft it onto
a new one then that be it's like you just planted that
vine that new that branch and then you should have to wait
three years. So if you take a look at תוספות Tosafot תוספות
Tosafot says like this. Go back to the bottom of לו עמוד
ב lamed vav amud bet and he says one two three six
lines from the bottom at the end of the lines he says
like this: ואם כן v'im kein says תוספות Tosafot היך אנו נוהגים
מן הכרמים שעובדי כוכבים מבריכים אותם בכל שנה. heich anu nohagim min
hakramim she'ovdei kochavim mavrichim otam bechol shana. How do we how do
we take the grapes from the from the vines that the non-Jews
graft every year like new shoots onto the vine? אף על פי
שאין אנו יודעים ודאי שמבריכים כולם af al pi she'ein anu yod'im
vadai she'mavrichim kulam even though we we don't know that every single
thing is grafted אבל רמי לילך אחר הרוב. aval rami leileich achar
harov. Here he says you can't unlike what he's going to say
in a minute about חדש chadash you can't assert that the majority
are not grafted. The majority actually like are grafted. So what are
we going to do about this? Okay.
ואומר רבינו שמשון v'omer Rabbeinu Shimshon this is the ר"ש משאנץ Rash
mi-Shantz ששאל בעובדי אדמה. shesha'al b'ovdei adama. He went and actually spoke
to the farmers. Okay. He spoke to the what do they call
it the vintners and ואמרו לו שאינם חותכים הזמורה מן הסדן. v'amru
lo she'einam chotchim hazmora min hasadan. What they they don't actually break
it off. What you basically have is
is you've got a vine you've got an old an old vine
here you take a shoot and what you do with this shoot
is that you actually put it underground. Okay. This is called actually
you put it... excuse me. It's not... I see I actually misspoke.
I keep on confusing the two things there's הברכה havracha and what's
the other one?
No no no no no.
מרכיב. markiv. There's מבריך mavrich and מרכיב. markiv. מרכיב markiv is to
graft. מבריך mavrich is you take a shoot you put it underground
it comes up in a different place and then you cut it
and then it's like it's it's like and then it's growing anew.
So that's like a new planting. That's okay that's מבריך. mavrich. That's
what he's talking about. It's I don't know what the word English
word is for that. I have no idea. Layering? But it's not
it's not grafting. So that's what they do. They they start new
vines by taking them and having them come up in new places
and you cut them and that should be like a new planting.
So he says... it's not grafting. It's this. So he says... so
he says he spoke to them and they said they told him
שאינם חותכים הזמורה מן הסדן. she'einam chotchim hazmora min hasadan. They never
actually cut it. It always remains still attached to the old one.
And therefore it's not like it's been replanted. Okay. ואם כן הוא
יונק עוד מן הזקנה v'im kein hu yonek od min hazkeina it
still is is getting its nutrients from the old one. ואמר התם
v'amar hatam and says in ירושלמי Yerushalmi המבריך בזמן שיונק מן הזקנה
hamavrich bizman sheyonek min hazkeina the new one when it's still getting
its nutrients from the old one פטור מן הערלה patur min ha'orla
it remains פטור patur it's not like a new planting. ואם סיפק
v'im sipak but if it is חייב chayav and... but if it
is but if it is I
suppose if it's like cut then it's חייב chayav והוא ניכר היטב
כשיונק מן הזקנה ושאינו יונק מן הזקנה vehu nikar heytev kesheyonek min
hazkeina veshe'eino yonek min hazkeina and it's obvious whether it is or
not כשהזמורה יונקת מן הזקנה הרי הם נוטים לצד אחר keshehazmora yoneket
min hazkeina harei hem notim letzad acher the leaves I guess turn
away from the old
one וכשפוסק u'kesheposek and if you sever it and it stops getting
from the old one הרי הם נוטים לצד הזקנה harei hem notim
letzad hazkeina then they turn and they face. back to the other
one, I have no idea, I can't tell you. וסימנך, vesimancha, the
way to remember it is דהאי מאן דאכיל מחבריה, dehai man deachil
mechavrei, if you're eating food from your friend בעי לאיסתכולי ביה, baei
leistakulei bei, so you're a little, you're embarrassed to look at the
person because you're like receiving all of their largesse. So therefore, when
they're still getting from their from the old one, they're looking away.
Anyway, I thought that was a little cute. Anyway, Tosfos' argument is
the way we can drink the wine is cause of this assertion
that it's that they actually don't sever it and it's still all
growing together. What's the problem? Does it make it ערלה?
orlah? Grafting would also be a problem. So how do you deal?
They necessarily go to the apple farm, you know, and they have
some trees that are grafted,
so you don't make a ברכה? bracha? Right. So the הלכה halacha
is that by ערלה, orlah, if there's a ספק, safek, then you're
חייב. chayav. But the problem here was, Tosfos was saying is that
it wasn't a ספק, safek, there was a ודאי, vadai, there was
a רוב rov he said, that wasn't that way.
But could you say the ספק ספיקא safek sefeika and like you
don't need...
You don't need ספק ספיקא. safek sefeika. ערלה וכלאים orlah vekilayim which
are only הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'moshe misinai or whatever,
or דרבנן derabbanan are a lot more lenient if there's a basis
for doubt, okay? Tosfos' problem was that there wasn't a basis for
doubt. The problem is
חדש. chadash. No, I mean, exactly the משנה mishnah I read you
actually, it's actually quite lenient. The משנה mishnah I read you I'll
just say is, oh my god, the חב"דים, chabadim, I'm sorry. Anyway,
the משנה mishnah I read you was, it says like this, it
says בחוצה לארץ יורד
ולוקט ובלבד שלא ילקוט ביד. bechutz
la'aretz yored veloket uvilvad shelo yilkot beyad.
Like
you could actually go ahead and almost intentionally cause there to be
a ספק. safek. There's a lot more leniencies about this, okay? Tosfos'
only problem was was that he didn't even have that basis. Okay,
let's keep on going. Back to the גמרא. gemara. Okay, so now
we have this issue about whether מושבות moshovos by נסכים nesachim or
by חדש chadash means after the land has been settled or means
wherever you dwell. So the גמרא gemara says like this.
אוקי, רבי עקיבא, Okay, Rabbi Akiva, yeah, okay. לא קשיא. lo kashya.
מדאמר אביי, mide'amar Abaye, since Abaye says, I didn't even read the
the final line of that, מאן תנא דפליג עליה דרבי אליעזר רבי
ישמעאל, man tanna dephalig alei deRabbi Eliezer Rabbi Yishmael, that since the
תנא tanna that argues on Rabbi Eliezer is Rabbi Yishmael, who says
that מושבות moshovos means according to Rabbi Yishmael after you settle. So
that's the תנא קמא tanna kamma after you settle and it's only
in the land of Israel. שמע מינה רבי אליעזר לחומרא פליג. shema
mina Rabbi Eliezer lechumra palig. So Rabbi Yishmael says מושבות moshovos means
wherever you dwell, even out of the land of Israel, and therefore
Rabbi Eliezer is being מחמיר. machmir. Rabbi Eliezer is saying that חדש
chadash applies out of the land of Israel. שמע מינה. shema mina.
So that's clear and that obviously was the פשט pshat in the
משנה mishnah that Rabbi Eliezer was saying חדש chadash applies out of
Israel and the תנא קמא tanna kamma says only in the land
of Israel. Okay. Now the גמרא gemara says like this. מכדי, mechdi,
let's take a look. רבי ישמעאל היכא קאי? Rabbi Yishmael heicha kai?
On נסכים. nesachim. He's talking about the נסכים. nesachim. We said that.
בנסכים ביאה ומושב כתיב בהו. benesachim biah umoshav kesiv behu. Because you
can't say that the word מושבות moshovos means,
or what's the פסוק? pasuk? The פסוק pasuk was, what does it
say the פסוק pasuk was? כי תבואו אל ארץ מושבותיכם.
ki
tavo'u el eretz moshovoseichem.
You can't say מושבות moshovos just means the where, means the land
that you settle, because it says when you come to the land
that you settle. So it's only the combination of the two that
would mean the land that you settled. Otherwise, if it says מושבותיכם,
moshovoseichem, it could mean wherever you dwell. It's also based on what
someone said, there's a difference between ארץ מושבותיכם eretz moshovoseichem and בכל
מושבותיכם. bechol moshovoseichem. So ביאה ומושב כתיב בהו. biah umoshav kesiv behu.
So it's only the combination of the two that presumably would mean
after you settle. Otherwise מושב moshav means wherever you dwell. גמרא gemara
says you're right. הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, that's what he's saying. וללמד
שכל מקום שנאמר ביאה ומושב, ulelamed shekol makom shene'emar biah umoshav, when
it says both of those, אינו אלא לאחר ירושה וישיבה, eino ella
le'achar yerusha viyishiva, it doesn't mean everywhere, it means only after you
settle. דברי רבי ישמעאל. divrei Rabbi Yishmael. And by the way, by
חדש, chadash, it says ביאה biah and מושבות. moshovos. Okay, so it
says both when you come and settle by חדש. chadash. So that's
the even though by חדש chadash it says בכל מושבותיכם, bechol moshovoseichem,
nevertheless, the argument since it also speaks about coming to the land
is the argument that חדש chadash at least according to the תנא
קמא tanna kamma would be only in the land of Israel, because
it says ביאה biah and מושב moshav like Rabbi Yishmael. So the
גמרא gemara says אינו אלא לאחר ירושה וישיבה דברי רבי ישמעאל. eino
ella le'achar yerusha viyishiva divrei Rabbi Yishmael. So גמרא gemara says אי
הכי, ei hachi, one minute, if Rabbi Yishmael's saying only the combination
of the two means after you settle and not wherever you live,
so אמר לו רבי עקיבא, amar lo Rabbi Akiva, Rabbi Akiva said
to him, הרי שבת שנאמר בה מושבות, harei shabbat shene'emar bah moshovos,
by Shabbos it says מושבות, moshovos, right? It says שבת היא לה'
בכל מושבותיכם, shabbat hi l'Adonai bechol moshovoseichem, was that the פסוק? pasuk?
בכל מושבותיכם. bechol moshovoseichem. ואמר רבי שבת
קל וחומר היא, ve'amar Rabbi shabbat kal vachomer hi, and he responded,
oh, Shabbos isn't a problem because of the קל וחומר kal vachomer
we know Shabbos applies in חוצה לארץ. chutz la'aretz. היא. hi. נימא
ליה, nema lei, why do you even have to say that? Say
it more basically then. אנא ביאה ומושב קאמינא, ana biah umoshav ka'amina,
when I say it means only in the land of Israel, that's
the combination of entering and dwelling,
and so Shabbos isn't relevant. Shabbos it just says where you dwell.
Okay. So חדא ועוד קאמר ליה. chada ve'od ka'amar lei. Yeah, that
and another thing. קאמר ליה, ka'amar lei, number one, אנא ביאה ומושב
קאמינא ana biah umoshav ka'amina
and Shabbos isn't a question, Shabbos I'm talking about coming and where
when it has both words when you come and dwell and Shabbos
only talks about where you dwell, does not talk about coming into
the land. That's number one. Number two, ועוד דקאמרת הרי שבת שנאמר
בה מושבות, ve'od deka'amart harei shabbat shene'emar bah moshovos,
even if I were just to pay attention to the word מושבות
moshovos by Shabbos and think that מושבות moshovos by itself was significant
to mean the land of Israel, I have an answer. שבת קל
וחומר היא. shabbat kal vachomer hi. Anyway, so that's not such a
convincing read, but nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara says that even רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael does not deny that מושבות moshavot by itself could mean
wherever you dwell. It's the combination of the two that means the
land of Israel, and it is the combination that we have, by
the way, by the case of what do you call it? of
חדש. Chadash.
חדש Chadash was the combination before רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva raised his
קשיא. kasha.
No he didn't, only on the עמוד ב. amud beis. He didn't
say it in the actual ברייתא. baraisa.
אמר ללמד שכל מקום שאתם
מושבין.
amar l'lamed shekol makom
she'atatem moshvin.
Yeah, that's how the גמרא Gemara modifies the ברייתא, baraisa,
but then comes רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva after that, right? הרי שבת.
Harei Shabbos.
I understand, but שבת Shabbos it doesn't say ביאה, bi'ah, it only
says
מושבות. moshavot. Okay,
so whatever. Moving on. So the גמרא Gemara says... the גמרא Gemara
re-read רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael and then רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva didn't
make sense because there's no way of challenging שבת. Shabbos. שבת Shabbos
doesn't say ביאה. bi'ah. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara anyway says like
this. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara says: Okay, במאי קמיפלגי? b'mai kamifligi?
What's the debate? בקירוב נסכים במדבר קמיפלגי. b'keruv nesachim b'midbar kamifligi. Meaning,
why... why actually does... why does רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva argue on
רבי ישמעאל? Rabbi Yishmael? Because the question is whether you assume they
brought the נסכים nesachim in the מדבר. midbar. Because the מדבר midbar
was so... meaning whether an individual brought the נסכים nesachim on the
במת יחיד. bamat yachid. Right, as it's clear from the פסוקים pesukim
that a קרבן ציבור korban tzibur had נסכים nesachim even when they
were bringing it in the מדבר, midbar, like it's clear about the
קרבנות korbanos that it speaks about there. But the question is would
an individual bring it?
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael סבר לא קירבו נסכים במדבר. savar lo keruv
nesachim b'midbar. They didn't. So when the תורה Torah speaks about when
you come into the land you'll bring the נסכים, nesachim, what's the
חידוש chiddush of the תורה? Torah? So for רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
the חידוש chiddush of the תורה Torah was you as an individual
will bring your נסכים nesachim on a במת יחיד. bamat yachid. You're
not doing it now in the מדבר midbar and that's the חידוש.
chiddush. But since it's limited to a במת יחיד, bamat yachid, again
בארץ מושבותיכם b'eretz moshvoseichem could not mean wherever you are, it has
to mean after you settle. For רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva סבר קירבו
נסכים במדבר. savar keruvu nesachim b'midbar. No, no, no. They already brought
it, the individuals on the במת יחיד. bamat yachid. So if they
were already bringing the individuals on the במת יחיד bamat yachid in
the מדבר, midbar, what does the תורה Torah mean when you enter
the land you'll bring נסכים? nesachim? What's the חידוש? chiddush? You already
bring נסכים. nesachim. So the חידוש chiddush is you'll bring it even
on a במת יחיד. bamat yachid. You'll bring it
בכל מושבותיכם, b'chol moshvoseichem, wherever you are. Right? Everybody get it? Meaning,
for רבי... for רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael. you would only bring it
on the במה גדולה. bama gedola. Okay. So you'd only bring it
on the במה גדולה. bama gedola. What does בכל מושבותיכם b'chol moshvoseichem
mean? בכל מושבותיכם b'chol moshvoseichem cannot mean on all your individual במות
bamos because he said you would not bring it on the individual
במות. bamos. So... or בכל מושבותיכם b'chol moshvoseichem means, or not בכל
מושבותיכם b'chol moshvoseichem but בארץ מושבותיכם. b'eretz moshvoseichem. Anyway, it does not
mean the individual במות. bamos. It means after you've settled because they
would only bring it on the במה... bama... and that's the חידוש
chiddush of the פסוק. pasuk. That outside in the מדבר midbar they
didn't bring it on the במת יחיד. bamat yachid. On the במה
גדולה, bama gedola, even on a במה גדולה bama gedola there was...
you didn't bring it. You enter in, you'll bring it on a
במה גדולה. bama gedola. Okay, that's רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael And בארץ
מושבותיכם b'eretz moshvoseichem cannot mean individual ones because he said you wouldn't
bring it on individual ones. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said they were
already bringing it in a במה גדולה bama gedola in the מדבר.
midbar. So what does it mean when you enter the land you'll
bring it? Of course you've already been bringing it. The only thing
it must be telling you is when you enter the land you'll
bring it on the individual במות. bamos. And therefore since it's telling
you you'll bring it on the במת יחיד, bamat yachid, בארץ מושבותיכם
b'eretz moshvoseichem means wherever you dwell, not after you settle. Okay. So
that's what the debate is about. Okay, now let's just read one
more... we're basically done. Let's just read one line to finish it.
The גמרא Gemara says,
okay, אמר אביי: Amar Abaye: האי תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל מפיק מאידך
תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל. Hai tanna d'vei Rabbi Yishmael mapik mei'idach tanna
d'vei Rabbi Yishmael. There's another תנא Tanna from רבי ישמעאל that... that
is the opposite of the תנא Tanna we just talked about whether
מושבות moshavot means everywhere you are or where you settle or... or
once you settle. דתניא דבי רבי ישמעאל: Detanya d'vei Rabbi Yishmael: הואיל
ונאמר ביאה בתורה סתם ופרט לך הכתוב באחד מהן לאחר ירושה וישיבה...
Hu'il vene'emar bi'ah batorah stam uferat lecha hakatuv b'achad mehen l'achar yerusha
v'yeshiva... You know what, it's already 8:30. So unfortunately we'll have to
stop here. We'll pick up with this tomorrow.